[Music]
when it comes to the amount of steroid
hormones we're exposed to in the food
supply milk products Dair products
Supply about 60 to 80% of ingested
female sex steroids I've talked about
the effects of these estrogens and
progesterone in men and prepubescent
children how mil can take and Spike
estrogen levels within hours of
consumption but in terms of effects on
women I talked about the increased
endometrial cancer risk in
postmenopausal women but what about
reproductive age women might Dairy
hormones affect reproduction we've known
Dairy food intake has sometimes been
associated with infertility however
little is known with regard to
associations with reproductive hormones
or anovulation meaning you know how
might Dairy do it by affecting how the
uterus prepares or affecting the ovary
itself the researchers found that women
who ate yogurt or cream had about twice
the risk of sporadic anovulation meaning
failure of ovulation so you know some
months there was just no egg to
fertilize it all now we know most yogurt
these days is packed with sugar even
Greek yogurt can have more sugar than a
double chocolate glazed cake Dunkin
Donut but they control for that and the
results remained after adjusting for the
sugar content which suggests that the
risk of anovulation was independent of
the sugar content included in many
yogurts now we don't know if this is
just a a fluke or exactly what the
mechanism might be but if women skip
ovulation here or there throughout their
life I mean might they end up with a
larger ovarian reserve of eggs I mean uh
women are starting to have their first
baby later and later there's been a rise
in women having babies in their late 30s
and 40s we used to think that uh women's
ovarian reserve of eggs stayed
relatively stable until rapid decline at
about age 37 but now we know it appears
to be more of a gradual loss of eggs
over time um here's what the graph looks
like where there's a steady loss
starting at Peak fertility at one's 20s
this is uh measuring anof folicle count
which is a an ultrasound test where you
can just count the number of like you
know next batter up eggs in the ovaries
uh it's probably the best reflection of
true reproductive age it's a measure of
ovarian reserve how many eggs a woman
has left okay so what does this have to
do with diet researchers at Harvard
looked at the associations between
various protein intakes with ovarian
anop folicle counts among women having
trouble getting pregnant
even though diminished ovarian reserve
is is one of the major causes of female
infertility the process leading to
reproductive deterioration with age is
still poorly understood in light of
women delaying pregnancy until older age
the identification of reversible factors
that may affect the individual decline
might be of significant clinical value
so they did ultrasounds on all the women
and studied their diets and concluded
that higher Dairy protein was associated
with lower anal follicle count in other
words accelerated ovarian aging here's
what the graph looked like in nonsmokers
significantly lower ovarian reserve at
the highest Dairy intake which would be
like 3 ounces of cheese a day compared
to the lowest Dairy intake okay but what
do these numbers mean in terms of
biological age is is 16.9 down to 12.7
really that much of a difference if you
look at women with really robust ovaries
a follicle count of 16.9 would be like
what you might see in a 36 or 37 year
old whereas 12.7 what you see in women
eating the most Dairy is like what you
would see in a really fertile 50y old so
we're talking years worth of ovarian
aging between the highest and lowest
Dairy consumers well it wasn't possible
for the researchers to identify the
underlying mechanism linking higher
Dairy protein intake with lower follicle
count they had several educated guesses
one uh it could be the steroid hormones
and growth factor to the contamination
of milk products with pesticides and
endocrine disrupting chemicals that may
negatively affect the development of
these ovarian follicles and egg
competence regarding the hormones
studies suggest that commercial milk
derived from both pregnant and
non-pregnant animals uh contains large
amounts of estrogens progesterone and
other placental hormones that are
eventually released into the human food
chain with de take accounting for 60 to
80% of the estrogens consumed as I
mentioned before Dairy estrogens survive
processing pure both in raw and
Commercial milk products are found in
substantially higher concentrations with
increasing amounts of milk fat with no
apparent difference between organic and
conventional dairy products it's
important to realize it's not just cows
that have been you know injected with
growth hormones uh these hormones are
just in their bodies naturally and once
inside the human body these bovine
hormones get converted to estrone and
estradi the main active human estrogens
and following absorption Bine steroids
May then affect reproductive outcomes
it's imperative that further studies are
designed to clarify the biology
underlying The observed associations uh
this might be crucial uh given that
consumption of another species milk by
humans is a evolutionarily novel dietary
behavior that is the potential to alter
reproductive parameters and may have
long-term adverse health effects
[Music]